<elements>
  <info>
		<name>Axolotl</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
	  	<description>The Axolotl race for Initium-Novum.</description>
		<author url="https://github.com/Aeon-Inc/Initium-Novum">Karst</author>
			<file name="Initium-Novum-Race-Axolotl.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/Aeon-Inc/Initium-Novum/master/Races/Initium-Novum-Race-Axolotl.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
<element name="Axolotl" type="Race" source="Initium Novum" id="ID_Karst_INITIUM_NOVUM_Race_Axolotl">
    <description>
        <p>Axolotl typically dwell in or close to large sources of fresh water, such as lakes or rivers, where they form intricate communities with not only their own kind, but with many other beings. Originating from the Feywild themselves, Axolotl are fond of other fey creatures, and will often form meaningful relationships with Elves, Firbolgs, and Gnomes among other creatures, as well as many forest-dwelling animals such birds, deer, and small mammals.</p>
        <p class="indent">Expect to come across Axolotl communities around large lakes, rivers, and waterfalls in temperate climates, or even on the coast, although Axolotl are cautious of the ocean's harsh currents, salty water, and many predatory monsters.</p>
        <p class="indent">Once an Axolotl finds an activity they find enjoyable and fulfilling, it's very likely they'll stick with it for life. Many Axolotl are known for being incredibly talented tailors, cooks, artists, jewelers, musicians, and alchemists among many other creative professions. Known as an Axolotl's "knack" their creativity is believed to have been gifted by their mysterious divine creator simply known as "Mother Lake."</p>
        <p class="indent">As a result of this, Axolotl society has a strong sense of religion, emphasizing the acceptance and learning of cultures other than their own, as well as a platonic love for their community.</p>
        <h4>Appearance</h4>
        <p> Axolotl are short, amphibious humanoids that mature quickly compared to other sentient creatures. In place of skin they have a network of small, tightly woven scales, which can range from the deepest blues to the most vibrant pinks in colour. In infancy, Axolotl scales take on an iridescent sheen as the pigments in their scales develop.</p>
        <p class="indent">They grow no hair whatsoever, and posses large frills on the side of their head - their gills - which are essential to their amphibious nature. Axolotl posses large, lemon-shaped eyes that are often turquoise, golden, lilac, blue, or various shades of such colours.</p>
        <h4>Names</h4>
        <p>While Axolotl posses some subtle physical traits to differentiate between sexes, they tend to pay no thought to the concept of gender, and have therefore adopted a universally androgynous naming system. Additionally, Axolotl do not posses surnames, will usually take both parents' forenames as middle names, and take a kind of title in place of a surname.</p>
        <p class="indent">Instead of being named at birth, an Axolotl usually chooses their own name around 5 years of age, resulting in small celebrations similar to birthdays upon the individual naming themselves - a deeply respected Axolotl tradition.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Axolotl Forenames:</em></strong> Farnan, Alma, Braemma, Kai, Scaelen, Llana, Ymbrae, Moora, Rosen, Cali, Memnis, Aldyn, Yale, Vaal, Lilli, Psamanthe, Rahnia.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Axolotl Titles:</em></strong> - of the Stream, - Fleet of Foot, - Child of the Lake, - Gleaming Eyes, - Shimmering Scales, - of the Crystal Beck, - Eyes of Diamond, - Scales of Sunlight, - Mother's Pup.</p>
        <h4>Axolotl Traits</h4>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Intelligence score increases by 2, and your Dexterity score increases by 1.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong> Axolotl reach maturity at age 6, and live an average of 60 to 70 years.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Alignment.</em></strong> Because of their naturally curious, altruistic, and social dispositions, Axolotl lean heavily towards a good alignment.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong> Axolotl usually stand between 2 and 3 feet tall, and weigh an average of 30 pounds. Your size is Small.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong> You have a base walking speed of 30 feet.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Amphibious.</em></strong> You are amphibious, meaning you can breathe both in water and on land indefinitely. You also have a swimming speed of 30 feet.</p>
        <p class="indent">Additionally, when underwater, you can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it was bright light, and in darkness as if it was dim light; however, you cannot perceive colour when in dim light or darkness underwater, so everything appears in various shades of grey.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Regeneration.</em></strong> If you are below half of your maximum hit points (rounded down), you can use a bonus action to regain hit points equal to your total level plus your proficiency bonus. Once you use this feature, you cannot use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Water Dependency.</em></strong> While maturing, Axolotl live almost exclusively underwater, and therefore a species-wide dependency on water has emerged.</p>
        <p class="indent">You must regularly submerge yourself in water for at least 30 minutes every 8 hours, and if you fail to do so, you become dehydrated. While dehydrated you cannot use your Regeneration feature, and suffer from disadvantage on any saving throws made to resist disease or the poisoned condition.</p>
        <p class="indent">While dehydrated, you gain 1 point of exhaustion every 8 subsequent hours until you submerge yourself again. Upon submerging yourself, you no longer suffer from disadvantage on rolls against disease or the poisoned condition, and you may use your Regeneration feature.</p>
        <p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read, and write Common and Sylvan.</p>
    </description>
    <sheet display="false" />
    
    <setters>
			<set name="names" type="custom">Farnan, Alma, Braemma, Kai, Scaelen, Llana, Ymbrae, Moora, Rosen, Cali, Memnis, Aldyn, Yale, Vaal, Lilli, Psamanthe, Rahnia</set>
			<set name="names" type="surname">- of the Stream, - Fleet of Foot, - Child of the Lake, - Gleaming Eyes, - Shimmering Scales, - of the Crystal Beck, - Eyes of Diamond, - Scales of Sunlight, - Mother's Pup</set>
			<set name="names-format">{{custom}} {{surname}}</set>
			<set name="height" modifier="2d4">4'8"</set>
			<set name="weight" modifier="1">30 lb.</set>
		</setters>
		<sheet display="false" />
    <rules>
        <stat name="dexterity" value="1" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
       	<stat name="intelligence" value="2" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
		<select type="Ability Score Improvement" name="Ability Score Improvement Option (Axolotl)" supports="Custom Ability Score Improvement Option" requirements="ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_ASI" />
       	<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
		<stat name="innate speed:swim" value="30" bonus="base" />
		<grant type="Vision" id="ID_VISION_DARKVISION" />
        <grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_SMALL" />
        <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
		<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_SYLVAN" requirements="!ID_WOTC_TCOE_OPTION_CUSTOMIZED_LANGUAGE" />
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AMPHIBIOUS" />
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_REGENERATION" />
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_DEPENDENCY" />
    </rules>
</element>
<element name="Amphibious" type="Racial Trait" source="Initium Novum" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_AMPHIBIOUS">
		<description>
			<p>You can breathe air and water. Additionally, when underwater, you can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it was bright light, and in darkness as if it was dim light; however, you cannot perceive colour when in dim light or darkness underwater, so everything appears in various shades of grey.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You can breathe air and water. When underwater you can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it was bright light, and in darkness as if it was dim light; however, you cannot perceive colour when in dim light or darkness underwater, so everything appears in various shades of grey.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
<element name="Regeneration" type="Racial Trait" source="Initium Novum" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_REGENERATION">
		<description>
			<p>If you are below half of your maximum hit points (rounded down), you can use a bonus action to regain hit points equal to your total level plus your proficiency bonus. Once you use this feature, you cannot use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>If you are below half of your maximum hit points (rounded down), you can use a bonus action to regain hit points equal to your total level plus your proficiency bonus. Once you use this feature, you cannot use it again until you finish a long rest.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
<element name="Water Dependency" type="Racial Trait" source="Initium Novum" id="ID_KARST_INITIUM_NOVUM_RACIAL_TRAIT_WATER_DEPENDENCY">
		<description>
			<p>While maturing, Axolotl live almost exclusively underwater, and therefore a species-wide dependency on water has emerged.</p>
            <p class="indent">You must regularly submerge yourself in water for at least 30 minutes every 8 hours, and if you fail to do so, you become dehydrated. While dehydrated you cannot use your Regeneration feature, and suffer from disadvantage on any saving throws made to resist disease or the poisoned condition.</p>
           <p class="indent"> While dehydrated, you gain 1 point of exhaustion every 8 subsequent hours until you submerge yourself again. Upon submerging yourself, you no longer suffer from disadvantage on rolls against disease or the poisoned condition, and you may use your Regeneration feature.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>
            <p>You must regularly submerge yourself in water for at least 30 minutes every 8 hours, and if you fail to do so, you become dehydrated. While dehydrated you cannot use your Regeneration feature, and suffer from disadvantage on any saving throws made to resist disease or the poisoned condition.</p>
            <p class="indent">While dehydrated, you gain 1 point of exhaustion every 8 subsequent hours until you submerge yourself again. Upon submerging yourself, you no longer suffer from disadvantage on rolls against disease or the poisoned condition, and you may use your Regeneration feature.</p>
            </description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
</elements>
